Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo collection on Latin American Folklore
Library of Congress American Folklife Center Archive of Folk Culture
Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo collection on Latin American folklore 1904-1986 1940-1960
AFC 2005/008
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
174 published items
Azevedo, Luiz Heitor Corrêa de, collector.
Collected publications pertaining to Latin American folklore and musical traditions from the library of Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo, Brazilian folklorist and musicologist.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Almeida, Aluísio de.; Almeida, Renato.; Alvarenga, Oneyda.; Amorim, José Pimentel de.; Andrade, Mário de, 1893-1945.; Araújo, Alceu Maynard.; Aretz, Isabel.; Avila, Floriano Maya d'; Azambuja, Darcy, 1901-1970.; Azevedo, Fernando Corrêa de.; Azevedo, Luiz Heitor Corrêa de; Bastos, Rafael José de Menezes.; Bettencourt, Gastão de, 1894-1962.; Bezerra, Eduardo; Boglár, Lajos; Brandão, Geraldo.; Brandão, Théo.; Brasileiro, Francisco.; Brăiloiu, Constantin, 1893-1958.; Bécker, Zahara Zaffaroni; Carneiro, Edison.; Carvalho Neto, Paulo de, 1923-2003.; Cascudo, Luís da Câmara, 1898-1986.; Castro, Zaíde Maciel de.; Coruja, Antônio Alvares Pereira, 1806-1889.; Côrtes, J. C. Paixão.; Echenique, Sylvio da Cunha.; Eduardo, Octavio de Costa, 1919-; Ferreira, Ascenso, 1895-1965.; Ferretti, Sérgio Figueiredo.; Geisel, Amália Lucy.; Gomes, André da Silva, 1752-1844.; Gonçalves, Martin.; Halmos, István.; Herrera, Ataliva, 1888-1953.; Hessel, Lothar, 1915-; Hornbostel, Erich Moritz von, 1877-1935.; Lamas, Dulce Martins.; Laytano, Dante de.; Lessa, Luís Carlos Barbosa.; León, Argeliers.; Lima, Rossini Tavares de.; Linares, María Teresa.; Machado, Propício da Silveira.; Magalhães, Basílio de, 1874-1957.; Martins, Saul.; Martínez Furé, Rogelio, 1937-; Melo, Veríssimo de.; Mendoza, Vicente T., 1894-1964.; Miranda, Nicanor.; Mussolini, Gioconda.; Neves, Guilherme Santos.; Oliveira, Clovis de.; Pardo Tovar, Andrés, 1911-1972.; Parreira, Roberto.; Pereira Salas, Eugenio, 1904-1979.; Piazza, Walter F. (Walter Fernando), 1925-; Pimentel, Altimar de Alencar, 1936-; Pinto, Alexina de Magalhães; Plath, Oreste, 1907-; Querino, Manuel, 1851-1923.; Ramón y Rivera, Luis Felipe, 1913-1994.; Ribeiro, Darcy.; Ribeiro, Luís da Silva, 1882-1955.; Ribeiro, Maria de Lourdes Borges.; Schmidt, Carlos Borges.; Shaffer, Kay.; Silva, Alcionilio Bruzzi Alves da, 1901-; Silva, José Calasans Brandão da.; Siqueira, Baptista, 1906-1992.; Souza, Yvonildo de.; Spalding, Walter, 1901-1976.; Teixeira, Humberto.; Thiéblot, Marcel Jules, 1924-; Thompson, Stith, 1885-1976.
Subjects
Aymara Indians.; Blacks--Brazil--Music.; Brazilian literature--20th century.; Brazilian poetry--20th century.; Carnival.; Christmas--Folklore--Brazil.; Dance--Brazil--20th century.; Dance--Latin America--20th century.; Epiphany--Folklore--Brazil.; Folk drama, Brazilian--Brazil.; Folk literature--Latin America--20th century--History and criticism.; Folk music--Bolivia.; Folk music--Brazil--20th century--History and criticism.; Folk music--Chile.; Folk music--Colombia.; Folk music--Cuba.; Folk music--Latin America--20th century--History and criticism.; Folk music--Mexico.; Folk music--Venezuela.; Folk poetry--Brazil.; Folklore--Argentina.; Folklore--Brazil--20th century--History and criticism.; Folklore--Brazil--20th century.; Folklore--Chile.; Folklore--Congresses--Brazil.; Folklore--Cuba.; Folklore--Ecuador.; Folklore--Mexico.; Folklore--Paraguay.; Folklore--Puerto Rico.; Folklore--Uruguay.; Folklorists--Latin America.; Kamaiurá Indians--Rites and ceremonies.; Music--Brazil--History and criticism.; Musical instruments--Brazil.; Nambicuara Indians--Music.; Opaye Indians.; Proverbs--Brazil.; Saints--Folklore--Brazil.; Santeria--Cuba.; Tepehua Indians.; Traditional medicine--Brazil.
Places
Brazil--Ethnology.; Brazil--Religious life and customs.; Brazil--Social life and customs.; Venezuela--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Articles.; Bibliographies.; Poems.
Biographical History
Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo (1905-1992) is recognized as the most significant Brazilian musicologist of the twentieth century. As a professor and composer, he taught at major French, Latin American, and American universities. Azevedo worked with the Department of Cultural Affairs within UNESCO, and served as Chief of the Cooperation Services with International Cultural Organizations. The International Music Council (IMC), a UNESCO supported global network of experts working in the field of music, made him a Member of Honour, and he was awarded the UNESCO/International Music Council Music Prize in 1977.
Azevedo's involvement in folk culture began in 1937, leading to a chair in National Folklore at Rio de Janeiro's National Institute of Music. In 1941, he visited Washington, D.C., as a guest of the Pan-American Union and returned to Brazil with recording equipment loaned to him by the Library of Congress. He undertook expeditions throughout Brazil to document the variety of Brazilian folk music. These collections of recordings are now part of the Archive of Folk Culture at the American Folklife Center. In 1997, some of the songs were released by Rykodisc as L. H. Corrêa de Azevedo: Music of Ceará and Minas Gerais in the Library of Congress Endangered Music series.
Source: Souto Maior, Mário. Dicionário de Folcloristas Brasileiros. Goiânia, 2000.
Scope and Content
The collection contains publications pertaining to Latin American folklore and musical traditions collected by Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo, Brazilian folklorist and musicologist. The collection comprises monographs, articles, bibliographies, conference proceedings, and other publications about folk music, musical instruments, popular music, dance, folklore, food traditions, proverbs, children's folklore, traditional and folk medicine, local religious celebrations (including Christmas, Epiphany, and Easter) and devotions to various saints, Cuban santeria, Afro-Brazilian traditions, and anthropological studies of indigenous people of Brazil, among other topics. Most publications are about Brazil but some are about folk culture in Argentina, Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Ecuador, Mexico, Paraguay, Puerto Rico, Uruguay, and Venezuela. Many of the publications are dedicated to topics that appear in the Brazilian tradition of literatura de cordel. The items often contain marginal notes by Azevedo and inscriptions from the authors to Azevedo.
Arrangement
The publications have been arranged in alphabetical order by author. Each publication was then assigned a unique identifying number and contains a flag indicating that unique number. Many of the publications contain inscriptions from authors and marginal notes by Azevedo. All of the items with inscriptions are noted in the bibliography.
Access
Collection is open for reseach. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact. Duplication of the collection materials may be governed by copyright and other restrictions.
Acquisition
In 1999, the Library of Congress purchased a large collection of material from the widow of Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo, Violeta Corrêa de Azevedo. Most of the collection went to the Music Division but Iêda Siqueira Wiarda of the Hispanic Division facilitated the transfer of the material related to folk traditions to the American Folklife Center in August 2005, with the assistance of Michael Taft and Sarah Bradley Leighton.
Related Materials
Related collections of audio recordings and a photograph album created by Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo and others are in the American Folklife Center, Library of Congress: Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo and E. Nogueira França recordings from Goiânia, Brazil (AFC 1943/015); Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo and E. Nogueira França recordings from Ceará, Brazil (AFC 1945/008); Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo and E. Silva Novo collection of folksongs of Minas Gerais, Brazil (AFC 1948/002); and Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo photograph album (AFC 2017/046). Related papers, including correspondence, are in the Luiz Heitor Corrêa de Azevedo collection, Music Division, Library of Congress.
CONTAINER LIST
- Acuña, Australia. Los Bailes Coloniales. [Place of publication, publisher, and date of publication not identified] (Box-item 1/1)
  Los Bailes Coloniales is divided in three parts. The first part describes the dance that is connected to three short poems. The second part presents the poems "El Aire", "La Resbalosa" o "Refalosa," and "Cuando." The last part contains the musical nototation for each poem.
- Almeida, Aluísio de. 142 Histórias Brasileiras Colhidas em São Paulo. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/2)
  A collection of folkloric narratives from São Paulo that won an award from the National Institution of Folklore in Brazil.
- Almeida, Renato. A Influência da Música Negra no Brasil. Junta Distrital do Porto, no date. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/3)
  A brief study on the influence of African music in Brazil.
- Almeida, Renato. Música e Dança Folclóricas. Rio de Janeiro: Campanha de Defesa do Folclore Brasileiro, 1968. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/4)
  This brief study describes some of the characteristics of folk music and dance in Brazil.
- Alvarenga, Oneyda. "Cateretês do Sul de Minas Gerais." Em Separata da Revista do Arquivo Municipal, vol 30. Book 1 part 1. São Paulo: Departamento de cultura, 1937. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/5)
  This study illustrates the various elements of the cateretê in Minas Gerais, Brazil. Cateretê is a dance characterized by dancing without touching based on an old tradition of fathers not allowing their daughters to dance arm in arm with their partners.
- Amorim, José Pimentel de. Medicina Popular em Alagoas: Rezas e Benzeduras nas Doenças e Ensalmos Outros. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. (Box-item 1/6)
  Medicina Popular... identifies the curandeiros (healers) of the state of Alagoas, who act as shamans among the general population. In addition to a brief introduction to the curandeiro, the book describes the prayers and the natural medicines used to treat illnesses.
- Andrade, Mário de. Popular Music and Song in Brazil. Rio de Janeiro: Ministry of State for Foreign Affairs of Brazil, Division of Intellectual Co-operation, 1936. (Box-item 1/7)
  A short study about the popular music and song of Brazil. It includes lists of institutions in Brazil and other countries that keep and preserve Brazilian music material. The study also includes a discography and bibliographies of the music of the indigenous communities of Brazil and of popular Brazilian music.
- Araújo, Alceu Maynard. A Congada Nasceu em Roncesvales: Especial para a Revista do Arquivo Municipal. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educacão e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/8)
  Using the celebration that happens in the city of Nazaré Paulista as an example, Araújo describes the meaning of the music, characters, and movements involved in the congada, a religious rite performed on the street.
- Araújo, Alceu Maynard. Alguns Ritos Mágicos: "Abusões," Feitiçaria e Medicina Popular. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1958. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/9)
  Documentation of popular beliefs, rituals, and natural medicines collected in São Luís do Paraitinga, a rural community in the state of São Paulo, Brazil.
- Araújo, Alceu Maynard. "Carreira de Cavalos em Itapetininga há cincoenta anos." Sociologia: Separata de Revista XI no. 4 (1949): 1-10. (Box-item 1/10)
  An overview of the horse racing tradition throughout history with a focus on the old practice of racing in São Paulo (Itapetininga).
- Araújo, Alceu Maynard and Vicente Aricó Júnior. Cem melodias folclóricas: Documentário musical nordestino. São Paulo: Ricordi Brasileira, 1957. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/11)
  This book is the musical documentation portion of an extensive sociological study that took place in the rural community of Piaçaburu in the state of Alagoas, Brazil. It contains a collection of folkloric melodies sung by the locals "during their happy and sad moments, and religious ceremonies."
- Araújo, Alceu Maynard. Ciclo agrícola: Calendário Religioso e Magias Ligadas à Plantação. São Paulo: Departamento de Educação e Cultura, 1957. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/12)
  This book introduces the fictitious rural community of Freguesia do Falcão located in São Paulo, Brazil.The author uses this fictional example to describe the traditional agricultural cycle and religious calendar.
- Araújo, Alceu Maynard. Folia de Reis de Cunha. São Paulo, 1949. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/13)
  Araújo describes the traditional custom of Folia de Reis in Cunha, São Paulo, Brazil, which starts on the night of December 24th, and is performed by a group of people who sing and play musical instruments to celebrate the birth of Jesus.
- Aretz, Isabel. "Correlacion entre las flautas de pan venezolanas y las andinas de alta cultura." Sobretiro del Boletin Indigenista Venezolano 6 (1958): 111-118. (Box-item 1/14)
  Comparison of the flautas de pan (flutes) used by indigenous groups living in Venezuela with those flutes used in Andean music.
- Aretz de Ramón y Rivera, Isabel; Luis Felipe Ramón y Rivera. Resumen de un estudio sobre las expresiones negras en el folklore musical y coreográfico de Venezuela. Institutos de Antropologia e Historia y de Filologia "Andres Bello," Facultad de Humanidades y Educación: Universidad Central de Venezuela, no date. (Box-item 1/15)
  A study of the African influence on the folkloric music and dance of Venezuela.
- Avila, Floriano Maya d'. O meio ambiente na obra de Alcides Maya 18. Comissão Gaúcha de Folclore, 1958. (Box-item 1/16)
  An overview of the work of Alcides Maya, a writer from Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Azambuja, Darcy. Principais lendas folclóricas do Rio Grande do Sul. Rio de Janeiro: Edição da Comissão Gaúcha de Folclore, 1958. (Box-item 1/17)
  A lecture given at the Catholic University of Rio Grande do Sul which starts with three definitions of folklore and then describes the main folk legends of the state of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil.
- Azevedo, Fernando Corrêa de. "Fandango do Paraná." Cadernos de Folclore 23 (1981): 3-50. (Box-item 1/18)
  A description of the Brazilian tradition of Fandango do Paraná, a celebration in which the fishermen living along the coast of the state of Paraná, Brazil, perform various regional dances. Among the many dances performed during the Fandango, the article describes some examples such as Anu, Xará-Grande and Xarazinho.
- Bahia (Brazil: State). Superintendência de Difusão Cultural da Secretaria de Educação. Caderno de Folclore Bahiano 1 (1953): 1-42. (Box-item 1/19)
  A collection of songs from the state of Bahia, Brazil.
- Bastos, Rafael José de Menezes. O "Payemeramaraka" Kamayurá – Uma Contribuição à Etnografia do Xamanismo do Alto Xingu. São Paulo: Universidade de São Paulo Faculdade de Filosofia, Letras e Ciências Humanas Departamento de Ciências Sociais (Área de Antropologia), 1984/1985. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/20)
  Bastos describes the steps of the Payemeramaraka ritual among the indigenous residents of the Alto Xingu, in the state of Mato Grosso, Brazil, called Kamayurá. In this ethnographic work, the Payemeramaraka tradition, its meaning to the Kamayurá community, as well as the vocabulary and music involved in this ritual are documented.
- Bécker, Zahara Zaffaroni. Poesía folklórica infantil del Uruguay: Contribución. Montevideo: Centro de Estudios Folklóricos del Uruguay, 1956. (Box-item 1/21)
  A collection of children’s folk verses in Uruguay, as recalled by the author. There are no informants or investigation dates identified.
- Bettencourt, Gastão de. A Baía e o Seu Folclore: Relicário de Tradições Portuguesas. Coimbra: Coimbra Editora, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/22)
  A discussion of the folklore of the state of Bahia, Brazil, and the Portuguese and African heritage that influences the state's culture.
- Bettencourt, Gastão de. A Inspiração folclórica na poesia brasileira. Coimbra Editora, 1954. [Copy 1 has a photograph on cover and an inscription.] (Box-item 1/23)
  On the influence of folklore on Brazilian poetry.
- Bettencourt, Gastão de. A Inspiração folclórica na poesia brasileira. Coimbra Editora, 1954. [Copy 2 has blue cover and an inscription.] (Box-item 1/24)
- Bezerra, Eduardo. Irmandade da cruz dos militares: Seus oragos, suas crises. Rio de Janeiro, 1927. (Box-item 1/25)
  Irmandade da Cruz dos Militares was a military league founded in the seventeenth century after a small church was built on the coast of Rio de Janeiro as a symbol of this brotherhood. This book describes the six oragos, or saints, of the Cruz church and documents the league’s involvement in the historical changes of Brazil.
- Biblioteca Nacional (Brazil). Catálogo de Livros sôbre Folclore Brasileiro. Rio de Janeiro: Ministério da Educação e Cultura, 1957. (Box-item 1/26)
  Catalog of books about Brazilian folklore that were exhibited during the celebration of the tenth anniversary of the National Folklorists Association.
- Boglár, Lajos and István Halmos. "La Flûte Nasale Chez Les Indiens Nambicuara." Acta Ethnographica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae 11 (1962): 437-446. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/27)
  An essay about the construction, use, and music of the nasal flute used by the Nhambiquara or Nambicuara Indians from the Amazon Valley of Brazil.
- Brailoiu, Constantin. "Le Folklore Musical." Musica Aeterna II (no date): 277-332. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 1/28)
  Brailoiu discusses the concept of "musical folklore" and provides an analysis of songs with variants in other languages and cultures.
- Brandão, Geraldo. Mogi das Cruzes: Monografia Folclórica. São Paulo: Prefeitura do Município de São Paulo, Secretaria de Educação e Cultura, Divisão do Arquivo Histórico, 1959. (Box-item 2/29)
  Research study conducted in Mogi das Cruzes, São Paulo. The city experienced an intense transformation and growth during the 1950s, and many traditions were lost. The author focused his work on the description of what was left of the Alvorada do Divino celebration.
- Brandão, Geraldo. Notas sôbre a dança de São Gonçalo do Amarante. [No other publication information found on this material.] (Box-item 2/30)
  This publication is a collection of mostly oral traiditions related to the cult of Saint Gonçalo. According to the author, the lack of written material sent him to different places such as Portugal and the southern state of Paraná, Brazil; includes a biography of Saint Gonçalo.
- Brandão, Théo. "Cavalhadas de Alagoas." Cadernos de Folclore 24 (no date): 3-43. (Box-item 2/31)
  Cavalhadas de Alagoas is one of the oldest celebrations in the northeast of Brazil. Twelve horsemen perform the four parts of the celebration including a visit to the town's church, horse racing, equestrian demonstrations, and retreat.
- Brasileiro, Francisco. Monografia folclórica sôbre o Rio das Garças. São Paulo: Departamento de Cultura, 1951. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 2/32)
  A collection of the legends and myths of the garimpeiros, illegal gold miners living in the region of the River das Garças in the state of Mato Grosso, Brazil.
- Brazil. Secretaria de Cultura, Esportes e Turismo. Folclore de São Paulo, Brasil. São Paulo, Brasil: Secretaria de Cultura, Esportes e Turismo, 1969. (Box-item 2/33)
  A brief description of different folklore expressions in the state of São Paulo, Brazil, divided into popular celebrations, traditional and popular dances, and art.
- Campanha de Defesa do Folclore Brasileiro. Defesa do folklore. Rio de Janeiro, 1961. (Box-item 2/34)
  Defesa do Folclore details the campaign of a national group of folklorists in Brazil to preserve the country’s folklore with the government's financial help.
- Canta Brasil: Humberto Teixeira. Supp. 10 (no date): 3-47. (Box-item 2/35)
  Humberto Teixeira was a famous composer who promoted the musical rhythms of northeastern Brazil, especially the Baião. This publication provides an overview of Teixeira's life and his music through pictures and lyrics.
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Cursos de extensión: Curso de folklore general y del Brasil. Copy 1. Brasileño: Instituto de cultura uruguayo, 1953. (Box-item 2/36)
  A short description of a course being taught on folklore of Brazil offered by the Cultural Institute Uruguay-Brazil.
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Cursos de extensión: Curso de folklore general y del Brasil. Copy 2. Brasileño: Instituto de cultura uruguayo, 1953. (Box-item 2/37)
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Cursos de extensión: Curso de folklore general y del Brasil. Copy 3. Brasileño: Instituto de cultura uruguayo, 1953. (Box-item 2/38)
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Cursos de extensión: Curso de folklore general y del Brasil. Copy 4. Brasileño: Instituto de cultura uruguayo, 1953. (Box-item 2/39)
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Diccionário del folklore ecuatoriano: Tratado del folklore ecuatoriano – I. Quito: Editoral casa de la cultura ecuatoriana, 1964. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 2/40)
  A dictionary of vocabulary of the folklore of Ecuador.
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. "El Problema del Folklore del Indio." América Indígena XIII no.3 (1953): 175-186. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 2/41)
  Discusses issues related to "Indian folklore."
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Folklore floridense: Contribucion. Lima, 1957. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 2/42)
  Documentation oral traditions such as tongue twisters and popular games from the city of Florida in Uruguay. It also describes the traditional party of San Cono, celebrated in the same region.
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Folklore minuano: Contribución. Florianópolis: Comissão Catarinense de Folclore, 1958. (Box-item 2/43)
  Folklore minuano relates to the traditions of the people of Minas in Uruguay. This publication illustrates the poetic, narrative, magic, and social traditions of the region.
- Carvalho Neto, Paulo de. Técnica de Investigación Folklórica (Experiencias del Paraguay). Montevideo: El Siglo Ilustrado, 1956. [Inscribed.] (Box-item 2/44)
  Techniques used in fieldwork in Paraguay.
- Carneiro, Edison. Folguedos tradicionais. Rio de Janeiro: Conquista, 1974. (Box-item 2/45)
  Carneiro gives a general picture of various expressions of Brazilian folklore. He describes traditional celebrations, dances, such as Batuque in Africa, and Samba in Brazil, the evolution of dances and musical instruments, and the samba-schools and carnival in Rio de Janeiro and Bahia.
- Cascudo, Luis da Câmara. Prelúdio da cachaça: Etnografia, História e Sociologia da aguardente no Brasil. Belo Horizonte: Editora Itatiaia, 1986. (Box-item 2/46)
  An ethnographic, historical, and sociological study about cachaça, Brazilian liquor made from sugarcane juice.
- Cascudo, Luis da Câmara. Tradición de un cuento brasileño. Caracas, 1952. [Inscribed on cover.] (Box-item 2/47)
  A study of a traditional Brazilian tale called "Persuasion." It comments on the origin of the story and includes examples of other versions of "Persuasion."
- Castro, Enio de Freitas e. As cavalhadas de Vacaria. Pôrto Alegre: Impr. Oficial, 1954. (Box-item 2/48)
  This monograph published during the National Convention of Folklore in 1954, describes a tradition called cavalhadas, which is a type of equestrian competition. This study shows the variation of cavalhadas in the states of Rio Grande do Sul and Paraná.